hey what's up guys welcome to sir pros
in this video we're going to be talking
about computer networks okay so what is
a computer network well first let's
break it down what is a network the
definition of a network is a group or
system of interconnected people or
things so it would be fair to say a
computer network would be a group or
system of interconnected computers right
and that's exactly what it is a computer
network is anything where more than one
computer is connected to each other
traditionally a computer network would
consist of desktop computers servers
printers etc but these days we live in a
connected world we still have desktops
servers printers but we now have a vast
number of smart devices connected to our
networks as well most of you will have a
mobile phone maybe a tablet security
cameras even smart lights are found on
networks these days and the list really
does go on and on so let's take a look
at some basic networks and we can see
what they look like first one that
should be familiar to most of you here
we have a switch a router a wireless
access point a desktop and a phone all
connected to the same network this is a
pretty common home set up it's worth
noting that in most home networks the
switch and wireless access point will be
built into the Rooter
generally speaking any network in a
single area is called a local area
network or LAN the LAN is usually
connected to the outside world using a
socket in the wall that your internet
service provider has installed this
socket connects you to something called
the wide area network or WAN
the purpose of a1 is to connect separate
local area networks together the most
obvious example of a one would be the
internet however businesses might have
private ones to connect multiple sites
together so now let's look at a more
business type network so we have all of
our office computers and these would
usually plug into a wall or floor socket
and these sockets will have cables
either running through the floor or the
ceiling back to a special room called a
wiring closet this room might also be
called a patch room or a server room in
the wiring closet all of these devices
will connect to a stack of switches
which are mounted onto racks
depending on the size of the network
there may be multiple wiring closets
which all connect to each other say for
example on different floors keep in mind
though this has been simplified to give
you a general idea
lastly we'll look at another type of
network that might not be so obvious now
I said before I'm sure you all have
smartphones of some sort
now these phones generally have internet
access via 3G 4G and even 5g well you
can think of these as basically a giant
wireless network for your phones
somewhere close to you there will be a
giant tower that allows you to connect
and get internet access the closer you
are to these towers the better the
connection is likely to be so these are
just some common network types and
really just an introduction to some
basic networked devices so the next
logical question is why why do we need
networks well let's imagine life without
networks for a second if we want to
print a document we would need to
directly connect a printer which is fine
but what if we have multiple computers
we would need multiple directly
connected printers right which isn't so
fine the beauty of a network is we can
share resources
if I have a file and I want to send it
to someone I can
they can also share the file with
everyone else
we can have shared printers that
everyone can use we can even have
servers that could store these files for
us of course
file sharing and printing is just one
example but this could be pretty much
anything and all of this even before we
start talking about the internet which
by the way is just a giant network with
the internet we can search for anything
we want
we literally have the world's knowledge
at our fingertips we have email we can
message our friends we can use hosted
computing telephone calls over the
internet and of course awesome YouTube
content so networking has changed the
world and how we live in it it's a topic
I still get excited about and there's no
shortage of new things to learn we'll go
over a lot of this in more detail as we
go this video is part of our full CCNA
course which can be found in the
description so please feel free to go
and check that out if you like this
video don't forget to Like comment and
subscribe
other than that thank you for watching
you